Guide to the Arthur Raper papers, 1959-1975
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Arthur Franklin Raper papers
1959-1975
C0095
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
4.0 linear feet 8 Boxes
This collection contains documents pertaining to the work of South Asia development expert Arthur F. Raper, including speeches, research and development project reports published by the Pakistan and Bangladesh Academies for Rural Development, Comilla and Peshawar, Asian Studies Center, Michigan State University and East-West Center Hawaii.
Raper, Arthur Franklin, 1899-1979
Box 2
Box 1
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Arthur Raper in 1977.
Biographical Information
Arthur Franklin Raper was a distinguished sociologist whose early work focused on rural social issues and racial discrimination in the South. From the 1940s through the early 1960s, he worked for several government agencies on problems of rural development in Bangladesh as well as other countries in Southeast Asia, North Africa, and the Middle East. After his work as senior advisor to the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, he returned to the United States and worked as a visiting professor at Michigan State University until his retirement in 1967.
Scope and Content
This collection contains documents pertaining to the work of South Asia development expert Arthur Raper, including speeches, pamphlets in Bengali/Bangla, research and development project reports published by the Pakistan and Bangladesh Academies for Rural Development, Comilla and Peshawar, Asian Studies Center, Michigan State University, East-West Center, Hawaii. Many of the documents within this collection have notes written on and within them by Raper and others, allowing for more insight into Raper's presonal involvement and opinions with these projects and surveys.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds other collections related to international development, particularly papers and records from individuals affiliated with the GMU Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution.
Index Terms
Corporate names:
East-West Center.; Michigan State University. Asian Studies Center.; Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla.
Persons:
Raper, Arthur Franklin, 1899-1979
Subjects:
Rural development--Bangladesh.; Rural development--Pakistan.
Contents List
- "Enlightened Farmers Camp", November 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Family Planning in a Rural Area: A Search for an Approach", circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "The Ford Foundation-Pakistan Project of Michigan State University and the Pakistan Academies for Village Development", circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets in Bengali/Bangla, featuring Maps and Illustrations, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Annual Evaluation Report", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Village Dhanishwar-three generations of man-land adjustment in an East Pakistan Village", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "A Survey of Cottage Industries in Comilla Development Area", July 16, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.1, No.3, August 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.1, No.4, October 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Adoption of Improved Methods of Paddy Cultivation in Comilla Development Area II", January 4, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.1, No.6, February 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "A Follow-up Survey on Seed Manipulation Scheme", March 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Adoption of Improved Methods of Paddy Cultivation in Comilla Development Area III", June 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "A New Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", July 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.2, No.2, July 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "A Survey of Attitude of Rural Population toward Family Planning", August 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Voluntary Group Adoption of Power Pump Irrigation", September 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.2, No.3, October 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Journal of the East Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Vol.2, No.4, January 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Pakistan Academy for Rural Development", June 1962-May 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Village Development, Comilla" Vol.3, No.1, July 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "A Rural Public Work Programme: A Preliminary Report" Vol.3, No.1, July 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", July 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Village Development" Special Issue, July 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla" Vol.3, No.2, October 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Accomplishment of the Works Programme of 1962-1963" (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Diffusion and Adoption of Agricultural practices: A Study in a Village in East Pakistan", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Education for Illiterate Adults", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla", April 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "Women's Education and Home Development Programme: First Annual Report", April 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "An Interim Report for the Communications Section", June 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", July 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Government of East Pakistan Basic Democracies and Local Government Department", July 1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", July 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "An Evaluation of the Rural Public Works Programme East Pakistan, 1962-63", October 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- "The Comilla Rural Administration Experiment: History and Annual Report", October 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "The Works Program in East Pakistan", December 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "School Works Programme: Comilla Kotwali Thana", 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla", January 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- "The Comilla District Development Project", May 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Rural Development in East Pakistan Speeches of Akhter Khan", June 4, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Pakistan Academy for Rural Development", June 1964-May 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla" Vol.5, No.1, July 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Pakistan Academy for Rural Development: Fifth Annual Report", July 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "Fifth Annual Report: June 1963-May 1964", July 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development, Comilla" Vol.5, No.2, October 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "Journal of the Pakistan Academy for Rural Development Comilla", January 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "The Supply of Family Planning Contraceptives to Different Unions of Comilla Kotwali Thana", March-August 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- "The Comilla Project: An Experiment in Rural Administration", April 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- "The Pakistan Academies for Rural Development Comilla and Peshwar 1959-1964, a Bibliography", Spring 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", May 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "Pakistan Academy for Rural Development: Seventh Annual Report", June 1965-May 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- "Comilla Pilot Project in Family Planning: Third Progress Report", August 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- "Cost and Return: A Study of Irrigated Crops in Comilla Villages", Ovtober 1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "Women and Cooperatives", December 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- "Technical Assistance in the in-service Training of Pakistan Civil Servants since 1958", January 1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- "Monthly Report: April, 1966" (Box 4, Folder 11)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", May 1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- "Production of Aman Rice in Comilla", June 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- "Monthly Report: May, 1966", July 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- "Changing Patterns of Administration in Rural East Pakistan", August 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- "Comilla Co-operative Experiement", November 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- "An Evaluation Report on the Progress of the Seven Thana projects under the Comilla District Integrated Rural Development Programme", September 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- "Communication and Publicity Experiement in Comilla", January 1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- "The Comilla Family Planning Projcet", April 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  *Note: The word 'Project' is mispelled in the title*
- "Rural Credit in Gazipur Village", April 1968 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- "Statistical Digest", May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- "Aus Crop Survery in Comilla Kotwali Thana", May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- "Tests of Irri Selections", May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- "Study on Insecticides for Rice", May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- "Annual Plan for Training and Research 1968-69", June 1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- "Pakistan Academy for Rural Development: Ninth Annual Report", September 1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- "Community and Agricultural Development in Pakistan", January 1969 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", April 1969 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Pamphlet in Bengali/Bangla, circa1970s (Box 6, Folder 1)
- "Terror and Brutality in Bangla Desh", 1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- "Tour of Twenty Thanas: Impression of Drainage-Roads", February 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- "What Price Pakistan?", June 13, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- "The Case for Bangladesh", September 1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- "Rural Development Programs for Adaptation from Comilla, Bangladesh", June 1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- "Prelude to Crisis Bengal and Bengal Studies in 1970", August 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- "Capital Accumulation Through Cooperatives", January 1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- "Three Essays by Akhter Hameed Khan", May 1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", July 1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- "Comilla Khadar", November 1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- "Role of Thana Training and Development Centre and Tip Team in Thana Irrigation Programme in Bangladesh", March 1974 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- "Land Holding and Co-operatives in Five Comilla Villages", May 1974 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- "Evaluation of Thana Irrigation Programme, 1971-72", June 1974 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- "Bangladesh Academy for Rural Development: Thirteenth Annual Report", June 1974 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- "Training At Bard", January 1975 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- "A New Rural Co-operative System for Comilla Thana", March 1975 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Accounts Manual, June 1975 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- "Women's Education and Home Development", June 1975 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- "Introductory Notes on Some Locally Initiated Development Projects in Bangladesh", June 1975 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- "Integrated Communication: Bringing People and Rural Development together", February 12, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- "Intensive Family Planning Information and Service Delivery Campaign", March 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Binded Publications on Rural Development and Crop Research, 1964-1966 (Box 7)
- Binded Publications on Irrigation and Rural Administration Experiments, 1963-1964 (Box 7)
- Binded Publications on Rural Development and Family Planning, 1961-1965 (Box 8)